In this video, we will be going over more
kinematics
examples. In all of my classes before, I
have
learned the kinematics, but I was really
struggling
and confused on how to understand these
questions
and I think what I needed was more
examples
on how to do it. So, I will be going over
a
couple of more kinematics examples to help
you
better understand and to solve kinematics
equations.
First of all, before we start, I'd like to
say
that having a formula sheet on hand every
time
you do one of these questions is really,
really
handy. This is a snippet from the AP
Physics
1 formula sheet and these are the main
three
equations that we use to solve kinematics
questions.
I have explained this in a previous video.
So, our first question is, a ball is
thrown
horizontally from the top of a 20m high
cliff
with a speed of 10m per second.
How far from the base of the cliff does it
land?
Keep in mind that it's thrown
horizontally,
so the speed is horizontal.
So, let's imagine this.
We have a cliff and we have a ball and
this
ball is thrown with a
speed of 10m per second.
The cliff is 20m high and
we want to solve how far from the base of
the
cliff. This is the base of the cliff, so
it's
thrown here and we want to solve this
distance.
Let's call this distance d. Now, first of
all,
let's see what we have here.
Well, we can first use our initial
equation,
distance equals speed times time, and
since
distance and the initial speed are both
horizontal,
you can do that. So, distance equals speed
times
time. You want to solve for distance and
you
have the speed. The speed is 10m per
second,
so 10 times t. And now, we can see that
the
only thing we need to solve left is t.
So, we need to find the time it takes for
the
ball to drop from up here to down here,
and
that depends entirely on the vertical.
How do we do this? Well, we know that the
acceleration
of gravity is, let's just call it 10m per
second.
Sometimes you gotta use 9.81, sometimes
you
use 10. It really depends on what physics
course
or exam you're taking. But for simplicity,
let's
do 10. So, you know the acceleration
downwards
is 10, so negative 10m per second squared,
and
then the height is 20m, and the initial
velocity
going downwards is 0m per second, because
the
ball is thrown horizontally, so it's not
going
anywhere downwards. Now, if you know the
acceleration,
the distance, and the initial velocity, if
you
look at all of these options, you can see
that
this one fits the most.
Let's first write this equation down. x
equals
x0 plus vx0t plus 1 over 2 at
squared. So, x is
usually representing distance, but when
you
use these formulas, it doesn't have to be
x,
it could be x, y, or z, or whatever.
So, let's replace it with y, because
that's
what we're dealing with. We're dealing
with
y. y equals y0 plus vy0 times t plus 1
over
2 at squared.
y means the final y position.
Well, finally, when the ball lands over
here,
y equals 0. And y0, this means naught,
which
means the original one.
y0, originally, it's at 20m, so originally
it's
20m, so y, which is final, is 0, equals
20.
The original velocity of y is 0m per
second,
like I said, so 0 times t.
And 1 over 2a.
What is a? Well, a is just gravity.
That's the only acceleration it has, which
is
negative 10m per second squared, t
squared.
And now, you can solve the equation.
You get negative 20 equals 1 over 2,
negative
10, t squared. So, what you would get is t
squared
equals 4. And
you cannot have negative time, so this is
inadmissible.
So, the final answer, it would take 2
seconds
for the ball to go from up here to all the
way
here. So, time equals 2 seconds.
Now, you have the time. You can easily
solve
for the distance. d equals 10 times 2,
which
is 20m. And that would be the answer for
your
first question. So, as you can see, what
it
really is, is finding the correct formula
to
use for a question. Now, let's go to a bit
more
different question. A ball is thrown at a
speed
of 20m per second at an angle of 30
degrees
above the horizontal. Find the total time
it
stays in the air. So, it's thrown like
this. This is 30 degrees.
And its projectile will be like a
parabola,
and it lands all the way here.
And you want to solve for time.
So, what do we do, first of all? What
defines
time, first of all? Does the x-velocity
matter?
No, because time depends solely on y in
this
case. Because
y is what defines the ball when it's
dropped.
When the y equals 0, the ball does not
stay
in the time. So, anything before y equals
0,
the ball is staying in the air. X does not
matter.
And that's one of the most important
things
you need to know for this question. So,
now,
like we usually do with angle questions,
we
want to split this velocity vector into
two
components, the x and y. So, 30.
But we don't need the x one, we only need
the
y one. The y-velocity.
Y, v of y. And we know this is 20 metres
per
second. So, what would the y-velocity be?
Well, if you have the hypotenuse, which is
20,
and you have the angle, which is 30, y
would
just be the opposite, so sine. So, v of y
equals
20 sine times 30 degrees, which is 10
metres per second. So, originally, the
ball
is going 10 metres per second up.
So, v y naught equals 10 metres per
second.
And we know that the acceleration is,
again,
negative 10 metres per second because of
gravity.
And one more thing, we have the final and
initial
y-value. They both start and end at y
equals
0. So, y naught equals 0, and y final
equals 0. So, looking at the formula
sheet,
the one that we could use would be this
one.
Because you have x, or y final, x-initial,
y
naught, v x-initial, or the initial
y-velocity,
and the acceleration. So, you can just
solve
for t. So, x equals x-initial plus v
naught x-initial t plus, I'm just copying
this
formula down. And now, we can replace our
variables
with it. So, x would just be the initial
position,
which is 0. x-initial would be 0 as well.
The initial velocity, as we calculated, is
metres per second, times t, plus 1 over 2,
the
acceleration is negative 10, times t
squared.
And, now we get 0 equals 10 t minus 5 t
0 equals 2 t minus t squared.
So, t can either be 0, because if you
factor
out t, or it could be positive 2, because
minus t, so that equals 0, you get 2.
Let me just expand it, if you guys don't
get
it. 2 minus t.
Alright. Now, which one do we know is the
correct
one? Well, what is it at 0 seconds?
At 0 seconds, the ball is still here, at y
equals
0. And that's correct, because we were
solving
for the times in which the ball was at y
equals
0. But, at 2 seconds, that's when time
already
passed, and it hit y equals 0 again.
So, that would be here. So, this would be
your
answer. 2 seconds.